[Music]
hey folks
welcome to the dark horse podcast live
stream
number 47. six 40
46 it's 46. i'm jumping the gun on 47.
that explains why you have said nothing
about this episode
being a prime number because 46 of
course is not a prime number
it's not no but 47 is right
yeah that's what i was thinking all
right well now that we've gotten that
important piece of mathematical business
out of the way
it is time to get to the state of
civilization which i have to tell you
folks
it's not good we've got trouble i think
first though we should note that um
here in portland oregon we can breathe
again uh it was it was a long time
coming and for those of you who weren't
actually here in the pacific northwest
you may have thought we were being
engaging a little hyperbole it was bad
but you know everyone's experienced
bad error before but um it was
really unprecedented in our experience
and and we've been in
we've been near fires before uh so you
know we actually
it maxed out the aqi scale we were above
500 for a while and it barely dipped out
of hazardous for almost 10 days
and two nights ago a storm came through
which before it started pouring involved
lightning which of course is
terrifying that more fires would be
started but
it rains sufficiently that we are now
breathing easy
for the first time in almost two weeks a
week and a half
uh and it feels terrific it does it
feels
spectacular and actually i can even see
the sun shining out the window which is
uh
it's new we got little glimmers of it
before but uh with the
there's actual uh sun peeking through
the trees actual shadows that aren't
that
horrifying sort of apocalyptic yellow
yeah the yellow is uh at least for the
moment
gone i will say i i was thinking back
and i don't know for sure if this is
right but
i think that this smoke plus coveted
thing
caused me to spend um more time
in our house not going anywhere than any
other point in my
life other than maybe if i was really
sick at some point maybe i spent that
much time
not going anywhere but it was just
really oppressive yeah and i think
what you said to me was a little bit
more clear than that i think because
what you just said would suggest that
you're talking about since march
and obviously the lockdowns in march
were tough um but
really it was this 10 days of being
locked in our home
and what you had said to me was you know
we couldn't even go outside
and isn't is this maybe the longest
period of time that either of us have
practically never been outside you know
we went to the mailbox i tried to take
the dog on a couple of walks you know
fully massed up but it was
horrifying and oppressive so this really
did
lock us down in a way that i think gave
me at least a little bit more
empathy we talked about during the early
covet lockdowns of how hard this would
be for people living
in cramped apartment quarters for
instance with no real
um outside to go to but you know even
even then
there is presumably usually some place
you can go even if it's not
even if it's not nature you know even if
it's just an urban scape
and uh there was really nothing to be
done here yeah now that that is exactly
what i mean so it's like the combination
of you couldn't
go somewhere there was no indoor space
that was being filtered to go to yeah it
could go to a movie
because of covid right and um you know
we've been talking a lot about covet and
the fact that the loophole
in the logic of covid is that the
outdoors are safe and so you should
drink it in and then this suddenly
descended on us
um so actually in our in our household
we're trying to reconstruct exactly when
this had happened and
i had gone out on a bike ride and
i hit a bridge over the willamette and i
could see this very
unnatural cloud and it was
perceptibly moving our direction so i
contacted you and said you know probably
ought to close the windows because
it looks like smoke is coming but i had
no idea that we were really talking
about
more than a week that was 12 days ago
yeah 12 days ago
and so anyway the degree to which it has
affected
the ability to think and you know i i
you and i have talked about whether the
smoke itself
was having some impact or whether that's
just simply you know time seemed to
grind to a
halt where it had been operating very
bizarrely since kovid
you know where months pass and um you
don't realize where they've gone
in this case it just seemed like it
stopped yeah no but i i do think
i've said something about smoke toxicity
on the last show not
we know with no specificity implied i
don't know
what um what the particulate matter or
other things in the smoke might actually
be doing but
um you know in addition the new and
extreme technical
troubles that we were having with the
podcast with the live stream
have since we were able to open up the
windows yesterday and get air flow
um largely disappeared right which
raises
so uh i i know you all are probably not
that interested in the tech
underlying this but i do think what we
have been facing on this front
raises very interesting questions
because we did have this amazing set of
failures and after what must have been
25 hours of my time in addition to all
of the time that zach spent
troubleshooting we did narrow it down
quite a bit
and it turns out we were right it was
interference now where the interference
comes from we don't know but the
interesting thing is it seems to affect
not every single device in the house
that uses hdmi
but only devices that use hdmi including
our television which uses a little
chromecast
uh device to allow us to get
hbo without subscribing to cable so
something about hd hdmi has left us
vulnerable so
if you are if you are not seeing
glitches right now
um we are actually utilizing hdmi
as heather points out with the windows
open after
uh more than 12 days things seem to be
better which raises the spectre
of the possibility that something like
radon which has been captured in the
house which ordinarily would be vented
at some rate
um might be emitting something which
wouldn't be collected wouldn't be
captured by the hepa filters the all
house filters that are otherwise taken
care of um whatever particulate stuff
might be coming in
exactly it's not particulate and so um
anyway we're testing that possibility it
takes a little time to get a long enough
test to know but
um the degree to which even our house
was a little bit freaked out by
the degree of lockdown was interesting
yep
and we're still we're still recovering
um
but uh but here we are and uh
we're gonna start with with ruth bader
ginsburg i think we should
yeah so um if i may i just i found a
number of things
to to say about her to read directly um
both from
an obituary that was just published in
the new york times um she died yesterday
um she was a supreme court justice of
course
and also from um one of her most famous
cases the opinion that she wrote as
the majority opinion one of her most
famous cases and i want to read a little
bit from the dissent as well in that
case first to talk about
so um first just for those who
maybe have been under a rock for a
little while um this from
yesterday's 20 uh yesterday's new york
times obituary
uh which is titled ruth bader ginsburg
supreme court's feminist icon
is dead at 87. her late life rock
stardom could not remotely have been
predicted
in june 1993 when president bill clinton
nominated the soft-spoken 60-year-old
judge
who prized collegiality and whose
friendship with conservative colleagues
on the federal appeals court where she
had served for 13 years
left some feminist leaders fretting
privately that the president was making
a mistake
so that's interesting and of itself now
that's not linked and i can't find any
evidence of those feminist leaders
um you know prettying privately nor do i
understand you know is it just the
author of this
piece who had some private conversations
i don't know but um
fascinating uh that this person who
became
um in some ways this polarizing figure
this this
as the title suggests this feminist icon
uh
had had people had women feminist
leaders worried back in 93
why because she talked to people on the
other side so okay let's hold that in
in place for a moment uh continuing
quote ms ginsburg
started from the premise that she needed
to provide some basic education for an
audience that was not so much hostile as
uncomprehending
she took aim at laws that were
ostensibly intended to protect women
laws based on stereotyped notions of
male and female abilities and needs
the justices did not comprehend the
differential treatment of men and women
in jury selection and other legal
contexts as in any sense burdensome to
women
she said in a 1988 88 speech so this is
from
five years before clinton nominated her
uh for scotus
she added from a justice's own situation
in life an tenant perspective his
immediate reaction to a gender
discrimination challenge would likely be
but i treat my wife and daughters so
well with such indulgence to turn in a
new direction the court first had to
gain an understanding
that legislation apparently designed to
benefit or protect women could have the
opposite effect
so that's that sounds that sounds like
feminism to me right that's that sounds
like the kind of feminism that
um i always did get behind and would be
getting behind today if
um if it were the feminism of right now
move the cat so i can use my track pad
um let me
share a little bit from the 1993 article
again in the new york times
uh in which uh they announced that
clinton had named
uh uh says here ruth ginsburg
advocate for women to court quote
in her 13 years on the united states
court of appeals for the district of
columbia circuit
the 60 year old brooklyn-born judge has
occupied an unpredictable center
on a panel that has grown into rigidly
hostile ideological camps
she is ruled in favor of abortion rights
but has also criticized the 1973 supreme
court decision that made abortion a
constitutional right
saying it went too far too fast mr
clinton made it clear at the
announcement in the rose garden this
afternoon that he hoped her independence
from the right and left would make her a
conciliator on the court
tears rolled down the president's face
at the closing of judge ginsberg's
remark
remarks as she offered a tribute to her
late mother ginsburg said
i pray that i may be all that she would
have been had she lived in an age when
women could aspire and achieve and
daughters are cherished as much as sons
again perfect you know this i i see
i see nothing nothing to argue with
here this is just this is just brilliant
and so let me just
before we start talking share a few
things from
uh the united states versus virginia
case
uh which came before the supreme court
in the 1995 season
and and the opinion was written in 1996
in which it was decided that the
virginia military institute vmi which
for over 150 years had been male only
must open its stories to women so in
this case
ginsburg wrote the majority opinion
which ended up being a 7-1
opinion scalia now now deceased
uh justice antonin scalia wrote the
single dissenting opinion and clarence
thomas recused himself because his son
was apparently a student
at vmi at the time so it was a 7-1
decision
um she wrote in for the majority
although actually renquist wrote a
separate majority opinion so this was
five other justices signing on
um uh to this opinion she writes
in 1996 virginia maintains that
methodological differences are justified
by the important differences between men
and women
in learning and developmental needs but
generalizations about
the way women are unquote estimates of
what is appropriate for most women
no longer justify denying opportunity to
women whose talent and capacity place
them outside the average description
terrific so she's recognizing both the
possibility of population level
differences
and skills and desires and and
interests while also saying you have to
allow
for individuals to to not be average
of course you do of course you do also
she writes
inherent differences between men and
women we have come to appreciate remain
cause for celebration but not for
denigration of the members of either sex
or for artificial constraints on an
individual's opportunity
so she's here doing the thing that so
many modern
activists want to deny she is saying yes
men and women
are on average different but that
doesn't mean that we get to
discriminate on that basis so one more
thing
scalia writes the dissent and in it he
says
much of the court's opinion is devoted
to deprecating the closed-mindedness of
our forebears with regard to women's
education
and even with regard to the treatment of
women in areas that have nothing to do
with education
closed-minded they were as every age is
including our own with regards to
matters it cannot guess
because it simply does not consider them
debatable the virtue of a democratic
system with the first amendment is that
it readily enables the people over time
to be persuaded
that what they took for granted is not
so and to change their laws accordingly
that system is destroyed if the smug
assurances of each age are removed from
the democratic process and written into
the constitution
so to counterbalance the court's
criticism of our ancestors
let me say a word in their praise they
left us free to change
wow so incredible right like and agree
with the majority or the descent here in
terms of the conclusion
surely we can all find something in both
of those arguments
both from ginsburg and from scalia that
is cogent and coherent and causes us to
think more carefully
than we might have before about what is
right and what should be true
that that is what scotus that is what
the supreme court of the united states
is supposed to be doing
and i was i was amazed
to read this to read both ginsberg's and
scalia's
opinions in this 1996 ruling which has
come down
as um you know in some ways the most
important of her career
yeah this is uh it's remarkable and i
must say i want to make a note here
about unity and i don't mean unity 2020
i mean
unity the movement and unity the concept
that motivates that movement
right there are many of us who remember
a modality of the past that is rapidly
evaporating and you
quoting ginsburg and scalia here
who both have a piece of the truth
clearly yeah and
are operating you know scalia being uh
as polarizing a person as existed on
that court
and yet in what he says you hear this
sort of moderation
and decency that is being lost from the
landscape now
i'm going to do something i shouldn't do
i sent zach a link
to a short video that i just spotted
before
uh we went live here so you haven't seen
it and i'm gonna have to tell you what's
in it since
all right zach is going to find it well
maybe i'll set it up while he's finding
it
okay um the video is of
the president the current president the
current president
inexplicably to me i think he has just
gotten off a helicopter
and the press i've seen this video
you've seen it the press alert him
to the death of justice ginsburg
and so it's his honest off-the-cuff
reaction
bizarrely soundtracked with elton john
for reasons i don't know i think every
version of the clip has that
yeah it's like playing in the background
somehow somehow it's in the ether
um zach do you have it you're working on
it
okay well in any case the thing i want
to point out about it is
that the decency of justice ginsburg
results in you know you watch trump
actually
literally take a moment i think to
consider the political implications
of what he's about to say which would be
true to character for him and
it would and of any political leader at
some level
well it's possible that you would have
um a sense
a human response that just overrode that
you would just know was okay
and so you wouldn't have to go through
that that uh checksum
but um but nonetheless i think he does
check and it's you know
i think uh virtually any modern
politician probably would
check and um and then anyway he says
some things about her
uh including you know that you
essentially you have to admire her
whether you
disagree with her or agree with her you
have to admire what she accomplished and
so
again in a very divisive president
uh her her death brings out this this
spirit
of reaching across the the aisle or the
political spectrum
and being decent to each other and being
decent to each other and she really
you know in going back through last
night and today just a little bit about
her history i was reminded that
a lot of her early the early cases that
she brought were specifically pointing
out
um places in the law where men and women
were treated differently
and men appeared to suffer as a result
so this is the way that she got in you
know this is this is the way
um that she ended up sort of being able
to bring the cases
before a you know mostly male uh
judiciary at that point and to get the
attention of mostly men
uh to point out that actually the you
know these arguments can sound very
lovely
um but they will end up being
discriminatory in ways that you
may never have imagined yes
um and the uh
the fact that such an amazing person
and force that her death at this moment
is going to cause and is already causing
um a catastrophe in the context of this
election is you know it's really it's a
it's a tragedy for democracy because it
is
um the the fact this has
implications for this election that are
truly profound
and you know apparently justice ginsburg
had vocally
hoped to survive through the
the seating of the next president so
that she would be replaced by someone
else now of course
it's no surprise that she would she
would have thought that this has to be
in the style of thinking of every
justice um
wanting to leave the court positioned uh
as they would have it
um on the other hand um
the fact of her death at this moment
and the fact of the implications for the
election is
like a gargantuan magnetic force for
those who would play games here
and frankly i will say i think it's
going to play right into the hands
of the president that the
democrats can be relied upon to be
vicious in attempting to prevent the
seeding of
anybody that trump would name yeah and
you know it's not as if this is without
precedent so obviously the
2016 election uh had a parallel
event and the republicans were on the
other side of it
um but uh anyway zach do you have that
video
okay you want to show it yeah
[Music]
i didn't know that i just you're telling
me now for the first time
she led an amazing life what else can
you say she was an amazing woman
whether you agreed or not she was an
amazing woman
who led an amazing life
um
[Music]
all right so uh did you see the biden uh
video so biden apparently learned of
this
uh on a flight and he got off the flight
with
clearly prepared remarks and he gave a
much longer
reaction of course um and you know i
will say
biden has been very prone to just
frightening errors gaps in his memory
and ability to articulate things in this
case
you know he does a decent job of
delivering his remarks he says some
interesting things about having
presided over her confirmation hearing
for example
he looks very very tired um you know
so there's no cognitive gap in what he
says but there is
a sort of jarring sense of like even
knowing that he's about to walk off this
plane
uh to reporters that want to hear about
this um
it's you know it's sort of touch and go
it looks but um you know
every politician is going to be tired at
this point in the presidential election
i'm not sure like
as you know i am no fan of biden i have
never been a fan of biden
and i have said as of months ago that i
would not vote for him but
i don't know that saying he's tired as
he gets off a plane is a particularly
fair criticism well you know it is and
it isn't because
the job of president has got to be about
as tough as any job with respect to the
demands you never know what crisis is
going to happen you never know when
you're going to be
called upon to you know switch it on and
and uh
you know engage heroic levels of
uh insight and ingenuity and all of that
that's part of why we're you know we're
electing someone and sort of
applying superhuman standards to them
and so what i would say is yeah sure he
frankly
he's too damn old and he would be tired
even if he was showing you know even if
he was bernie sanders and showing no
signs of decline
cognitive decline right the point is
we'd still have to say does it make
sense to
put somebody in such an important
position that is so grueling
right and in this case you know well
like i said i think
he did a fine job of what he said but
the fact that it does feel tenuous
i think is there's a legitimate reason
for concern there which is that somebody
this old is simply
prone to be unable to deal with uh
crisis aren't they the same age issue
yes
i agree i think uh trump is showing
signs and i'm
worried there too but i would say he is
showing
fewer of those signs but basically i
think we are learning
what i have come to realize is that
the number of people that i would
actually
trust in this role who are not eligible
by virtue of being too
young is not huge but it there are
several people
on that list who i think would be um
decent candidates for president who
don't
really yeah do you want to share any i'd
like us to talk a bit more about
ginsburg but um
this is this is a little surprising to
me who who
below the age of 35 you're just talking
about the age limit right like right now
in my own defense i would say that um
it's not that i would i do think there's
a reason to want somebody with more
experience but
my point here is simply that there are
people below this age
who um appear to have sufficient wisdom
to beat the candidates that we actually
have
by you know by a wide margin even though
i mean if anything 35 is younger than it
was
when that um that requirement was put
into
into law right you know because because
um
life expectancy is longer and we have
greater health
in our youth and middle age now so um
and you know we've had these extended
childhoods
where you know people are not forced to
become adults for a lot longer than
was the case uh back in the 18th century
yeah so um
you know i'm debating in my own mind
whether it makes sense to actually say
names out loud but i would just say you
know
it's not that i think anybody that age
knows enough but i do think there are
people that age who know
that they don't know enough and would
know how to process information they
would source
information well and and they would do a
good job so anyway
the overarching point is they should
have
the founders should have given us a
maximum age
probably the maximum age would be too
low in light of the fact that people
remain younger
longer than they once did um but um
but it is interesting yeah they would
the maximum age that you might choose
would likely have been beyond life
expectancy and so wouldn't have made
sense to do
right right right exactly um so
anyway uh
but i i think that's where we should
leave it okay um
and if we if there is a clamor maybe
i'll come back and talk about who
who that is young actually fits the bill
yeah
um so you know ginsburg
really did
change the the judicial landscape
um the legal landscape for women in
tremendous ways
and um that was true before
you know notorious rgb and you know all
of this
strange adulation late in her life that
became
uh sort of i don't know in in meme space
uh she she really was out there saying
and
part of the reason i read specifically
the quotes that i did is her
her recognition of without specifying
what they might be
of population level differences between
men and women
and her recognition that under the law
we must be treated equally because
for any for any overlapping
to normal distributions for any trait
they will be
um you know extraordinary men and
what's the opposite of extraordinary um
lackluster no lackluster is not the
opposite of extraordinary
um you know incompetent men and there
will be extraordinary women and
incompetent women
and the idea that um you know in the
case of a vmi and you know i don't i
don't actually
know um i don't exactly know where i
fall between these two opinions on this
because the
this was a this is a public institution
that for over 150 years have been male
only
and the argument was that it was
effectively a kind of
a militarized education that was not
mostly training people for the military
only about 15
of the the students at vmi apparently
went into the military
um and
ruth bader ginsburg's point uh was
women there are there are many women
although
probably not as many as there are men i
don't know that she says that but you
know my
my cystical brain goes like okay there
will be many women although not as many
as there are men who would benefit from
and enjoy and be educated by this kind
of education
and especially if the argument is not
that we are training
soldiers which is a kind of a different
a different argument potentially
although obviously women are now
also acting as soldiers then
basically what vmi proposed to do was to
create a separate women's institute
which of course did not have you know
you create something from scratch in
1995 or whatever and it's not going to
have the history
and the connections and it's you know
it's it's it's obviously a second-rate
solution
it's a separate but equal phenomenon
which of course results in a separate
but unequal
right result right exactly and so you
know are there
you know but are there not arguments for
um sex single sex spaces
yes single sex educational spaces
probably like both you and i have
actually attended single sex educational
spaces me by choice for five weeks i'm
college
over it at this point and you know you
you um
in junior high and high school um
until until they politely asked you to
leave and you came to the school where i
was
invited to leave i invited was it polite
though uh
very it was a kind of an elite school so
they were very polite and diplomatic
very sound
euphemistic in their invitation for me
to get the [ __ ] out
so anyway so i mean so both of us have
i have only five weeks experience at a
women's college and you have
four years of experience from a lot
longer ago well actually not that much
longer ago but when you were when you
were still
definitely a child right um let's put it
this way exactly the wrong moment to be
isolated from girls it was not i think
it worked out for you okay oh it did in
the end but that really has more to do
with the getting kicked out at the right
moment
than the being there in that stifling
institution yeah
but so so you who had um you know who
really
never felt like there were benefits to
you being in a single sex educational
environment between the
ages of uh grades of seven and ten
can you can you explain why um
at say the college level there might be
benefits to
an all-male environment of course right
so so do so well
um let's just say you know i
i don't think the benefits are net in
general on the other hand
um the consequence
well unfortunately any such analysis
would be largely predicated
you know unless we're talking about an
education with a
physical component and even then you
have to push it fairly far
before you get to a place where there
really needs to be
separation so any argument that is not
based in physical differences
in uh average capacity between men and
women
would be largely predicated on a
heteronormative viewpoint which would be
unfair to impose on this so in some
sense maybe
the answer is any explanation has uh
has dissipated you lost me at
heteronormative viewpoint
i'm sorry if you want to do that
really are you are you serious well i am
in the sense that there are places where
let's just cut to the chase okay
let's say because i i know you've
noticed but the world is actually
heteronormative
well hetero there's heteronormative and
there's the expectation that everybody
falls under that
so this then is again the population
versus individual level expectation like
obviously the vast majority of the world
is heterosexual which is what the hetero
and heteronormative refers to
right and um and that is
that recognizing that is different from
therefore saying that all the
all the world must be in all individuals
in it must be and anything
veering from that is somehow um off
or wrong or or or you know not okay so
this these these two things are both
true and this is again
exactly the distinction between
populations and individuals which
somehow
most people seem to have a very very
hard time of holding those two things
those two concepts
in their in their heads at the same time
men and women are on average different
and men and women as individuals should
be engaged with as
individuals they are with their
particular strengths and weaknesses
which
may well be different than you would
expect based on
their the diagnosis of your male or your
female
so we have arrived at what i suspect is
one of the five most important
principles
in the entire universe wow
yeah let's let's do it um okay the
principle is something like
a highly functional system
requires discretion applied
by um sober minds right and so
what you've outlined which i think is
perfect for ruth bader ginsburg
is that she was deploying a very
enlightened
understanding of equality right it's
exactly what we've been
arguing for here which is that
equal rights is a highly desirable thing
that should be
um defended uh vigorously
but that that does not mean that we're
the same
right and that these two things while
you know a naive person may conclude
that one has to be true for the other to
be true
a an honest broker will recognize that
they can't possibly
both be right and that the desire to um
to protect people equally is actually
unrelated
to the similarity of those people you
men and women women don't have to be the
same phenomenon and we don't have to be
suffering from an oppressive viewpoint
that has been
inflicted on us that separates men from
women in order to protect men and women
well but what that means is that you do
get to
a spot where you have to acknowledge
that actually here is one of the places
where difference
matters yeah right yeah well and um
you know it's it gets it gets dicey
right so
in an educational environment which is
in part even if it's not the majority
training men for training men
historically
for military duty uh the presence
of the introduction of a small number of
women is going to change the dynamic
it 100 is and so this is one of the many
many ways in which sex is not like race
and so you know when we talk about
whether or not
you know they're i don't even know when
it happened but you know our we're black
soldiers allowed
uh into the army to fight in world war
ii and i probably um that's probably the
wrong
moment in history but whatever but often
grouped together grouped together
and um but you know there was never
there never should have been
any reason at all to protect
in quotes uh you know white soldiers
from black soldiers
that's wrong that's insane there is
there is
nothing in in soldiering in
you know being a human that is different
in that regard with
you know between between races right but
men and women is different because this
is this is a distinction
that is 500 million years old in our
lineage alone
and so it does change the dynamic and
you know i i say that as someone who has
benefited
from the ability of women to move into
spaces that have been historically male
in some of those
spaces they weren't legitimately
historically male
but some like the military
may well function better without there
being a small number
of women present in every situation
right and so
uh let us point out that the
importance it may be that there is a
functional difference in how a you know
military
division functions when it's mixed sex
versus not
in fact you would expect it and what
rests on it functioning well is
something
that rises above frankly individual
protections in fact the entire
right for us to draft people and send
them into battle
you know is because your right to decide
whether or not to go
to go into battle cannot override our
right to marshal the force that's
necessary in order to protect
the thing on which we all depend and so
because we know that you need a
deliberative body
that is capable of recognizing the
uncomfortable
asymmetries and like i'll even take your
challenge about race here right and boy
this is a frightening thing to say
although
i don't think there's any reason that
this should be a it's not a difficult
logical problem at all
let's say that you had a situation in
which a military
force that intermingled races
worked less well was militarily less
effective
because of distrust between the races
right
the same logic applies you want to fix
that so that that's no
not true you want to address whatever it
is that causes distrust
between the races to compromise the
force militarily
but to the extent that the existence of
the nation might depend on grouping
people
with those they don't mistrust you would
have to have discretion to do that
as you corrected the thing that caused
the mistrust
yeah i don't know i don't know because
um you know recognition of difference is
certainly as you know older than being
human
what what social organisms do in part is
recognize individuals as
friend or foe or unknown and
characterize difference
and this is you know this is a basis for
tribalism and
racism and all of these things without
it being a justification for them it is
an explanation of them
at least in part um but
in in a country that
prides itself on being a melting pot
and um having welcomed immigrants to its
shores from all over the world
almost from its almost from its origin
story
um i i don't
know that i can imagine justifying
even the momentary um
sort of privileging of the the bias
in the ranks whereas whereas
um pretending that
a couple of super awesome badass female
soldiers
in uh you know in a remote place with
40 even super awesome you know
non-rapey badass male soldiers
may really change the situation and
that's that is
a that is a
that's that's older than sociality
that's older than
that's so much older than everything
else that we're talking about right
so i'm not making the argument you think
i'm making okay i'm not making the
argument that
race is such a phenomenon because
of course the thing about the way human
beings
actually work is that some of the stuff
is in the software layer and while there
is historical distrust between races
based in biology there is also
plasticity
that allows it to be refactored yeah
right
so i'm not arguing that this is such a
place what i'm arguing is
if it were such a place and the ability
of the population including all of its
races to continue
involved fielding uh military uh
um groupings that functioned
then that would have the priority right
so in the moment to win the battle
right and so really what i'm arguing
goes back to your point about ginsburg
which again i'm saying is
you know one of the five most important
principles in the universe and mind you
i was gonna i'm gonna have to sit down
and figure what the other four are but
um but the point
is it is the discretion that a
decent person who is capable of taking
in
all of the information not just about
our aspirations who we want to be
right but who we actually are and what
is necessary in order for us to get
where we're going right that discretion
is key and it is why the supreme court
was placed in the position that it was
placed it's why it's configured as it is
configured it's why
you have uh these you know terms for
life
um and to scalia's point it's the
the earliest documents the founding
documents of the united states
states precisely give us the freedom to
change
to not be limited to the biases of our
time
and all times we'll have biases and some
of them we can't even begin to imagine
yet right and especially the way he
phrases it his point is the things that
you are certain are true
that we will know in the future weren't
true right
that thing is why we have to have this
capacity to
to deliberate over over what what is
true it's quite an arrogance
actually um that he's pointing to and i
don't think i don't think he uses that
word but it's you know it's arrogance
it's hubris to imagine that now right
now we finally arrived
at the perfect moral center of humanity
and everyone in the past
got it wrong and no one in the future
will learn anything
more and now we're there we've arrived
and frankly we see this arrogance
in many academic fields and you know in
just about frankly every domain
like it's this we're there and
uh now history has stopped yep well and
you know where we're seeing it now that
is the most frightening of all is in
the goddamn tech sector right these
people
actually think that they know what is
true
with sufficient clarity that they're
going to go about labeling
beliefs as false that they're going to
so specify what you're talking about
here well for example actually this is a
something worth pointing out we
highlighted two
heterodox papers about um
about covid on our last live stream now
one of them i must say i have some
trepidations about
uh the yam paper um but
the yan paper makes arguments that one
can
evaluate now some of those arguments i
think raise questions
i think everything in that paper is
evaluable
it's evaluatable right it takes the form
of an evaluatable argument and in fact
i've gotten some correspondence from
people who spotted various things in
the same paper yep right um nonetheless
right the tech sector has decided well
that this is dangerous misinformation
and they have now
uh they have suspended her account the
lead author
the twitter account right and they are
labeling
those who would i think they're either
forbidding the posting of the paper or
labeling it as
misinformation now here's the problem
the other paper that
wasn't the paper that we highlighted but
the other body of work that we
highlighted
alina chen on the last broadcast
is the gold standard of evaluation
of kovid's origins
the tech sector regards what
the second body of work reveals as
misinformation in other words it's
decided that the true story of kovid
is natural origin so the tech sector is
acting
as kind of uh jury judge and executioner
but
as in a scientific framework like it's
pretending to be
to do the job of peer review in a
perfect world where peer review was
actually
assessing these things right it's a
completely
insulated unassailable kind of super
review yeah and the thing is we know
that the mechanism
by which the mainstream arrived at the
conclusion that this was clearly natural
origin
has again and again been wrong right we
knew it was the
wuhan seafood market we now know it
wasn't the wuhan seafood market
we thought that the spike protein
indicated uh connection with pangolins
we now know that it wasn't pangolin so
the point is look
this is the way science works the right
certainties fall away with never any
any even recognition that actually we we
said we were 100 certain back then
and we were wrong and i mean this is
something that you have done with our
children very effectively
when they make a claim and you say how
sure are you of that
any point that they come up with i'm 100
certain you say you'd be
really careful with that right because
there are some things that we can be 100
certain of you know assuming that the
sun rises tomorrow it will rise
in the east right it will it will it
will not come up in a different place
but uh for nearly
all observations that are parts of
complex systems especially if they have
social components
do not put your certainty at 100 well
and when you
have tried to put your certainty at some
percentage
keep track of what happens keep track of
your predictions and keep
track of whether or not your estimates
of your uncertainty
and your accuracy and your predictions
are getting closer and closer over time
because if they're not you're doing
something wrong
i agree although i would say you don't
need all of that caveat
about um things about which we can be
actually certain
like if the sun rises it'll rise in the
east even that
right now my point would not be that it
is worth spending
an iota of time worrying about the sun
coming up somewhere other than in the
east
my point would be that you need to
formally recognize
that everything that you believe you
have effective certainty over
is predicated on certain assumptions
which are themselves not perfectly
secure
right you do not know that you are not
having a um
hallucination that everything that you
believe to be true your own name
your relationships where you live that
all of that is not the product of some
um some scenario that you're unaware of
and in fact
we even now talk about such scenarios i
don't take them seriously because i
think the chances of them being right
are
virtually zero but they're not zero this
could be a simulation
right if it's a simulation then all of
the things that you believe about suns
coming up in places
isn't literal right it's something else
it's something happening inside a
simulation so anyway
my point to our children is if you say
i'm 100
certain that the sun will rise in the
east tomorrow
what you are really saying is that the
chances that it won't
are sufficiently small to be negligible
right you are not saying they are
actually zero and so um so the exercise
that i
i do run with our children is when
things are
substantially more uncertain than that
like you're
99.5 certain then you need to know the
difference between i'm rounding to a
hundred
i'm 100 certain it's going to happen but
the point is
what would you rate the chances of its
you know not
happening right well actually you can be
specific about it and
um that that exercise leaves you in a
a very different landscape because in
general people's beliefs are i either
believe this to be true or i believe it
to be false and if
every place you do that you substitute
the chances that i think this
is true are above x and that is enough
for
me to you know to operate on that
assumption
right then you are capable at the point
you discover that something that you
thought was
you know 95 and a half percent certain
is only 75
certain you don't have to switch camps
you can back off
your certainty you're still in uh
probabilistic territory as opposed to
black and white no nuanced territory we
are always in probabilistic territory
even
well no but you but the point i'm making
is that you just said switch camps yeah
and one of those camps is does not
understand itself to be in probabilistic
territory
even though it is right it is in that
camp
whether it is operating in that universe
whether it understands it or not and so
it's constantly making errors and so the
tech sector and its
um absolutely mind-boggling arrogance in
deciding that it is going to wade into a
landscape
where the mainstream has already gotten
it wrong a bunch of times and lots of
highly credible people are now looking
at the mainstream story and saying
here is where it is wrong right here is
the probability
that you know something like a lab leak
is true
right yes if you took a vote would you
find that mainstream virology
was you know more or less united around
the idea that this was a natural
emergence you would means nothing right
so the point is as i as i used to always
say to my classes reality is not
democratic
science is not democratic that's not how
it works
yeah in fact what's what's true is true
regardless of whether or not
anyone yet knows or believes it to be
true
yeah meadowwar i'm trying to remember
what the exact quote is but pb meadow r
uh nobel laureate um
once said something to the effect of
it's amazing how little effect
your desires have over what's actually
true that's good
see if i can find it while you yeah
all right um so in any case the
necessity of civilization functioning
requires
discretion deployed by people who have a
nuanced understanding of things and are
capable of balancing
various concerns right and
the aspiration to fairness does not
override
the subtlety as frustrating as some of
them may be
about you know the way
different populations like male and
female actually
substantially differ yeah so here's uh
peter meadows
said i cannot give any scientist of any
age better advice than this
the intensity of a conviction that a
hypothesis is true has no bearing over
whether it is true or not
it's interesting how that's exactly what
uh the quote i
almost deployed here means but the
wording is very different and i remember
i'm wondering if he may have said the
other thing too somewhere
but in any case all right so uh
we should uh continue with ginsberg if
there's more to say about
um about her did you have more uh i mean
there's there's plenty to talk about but
i
i don't know where you're going well
there's the question of this individual
and her
impact and her absence and then there's
the question
about the landscape in which her death
now
interfaces with politics and
the question is is it are we there sure
i'm not sure i have much to say about
the latter because it just looks like a
giant
[ __ ] storm uh it is it is this is a very
so let us say one of the things that
biden said in his remarks
was that um the number of days
i don't remember the exact number but
the number of days to the election is
actually
shorter than the minimum time any
justice has ever taken
to be confirmed right so that would seem
to suggest
that this is impossible and we should
put it off the way we did
in 2016. on the other hand
well um i don't know if you've seen
this if we want to show this from
august 30th of 2016 um
barack obama
saying summer's almost over senate
leaders do your job fill the supreme
court vacancy yep
so this is you know this is almost two
three weeks
earlier uh than we are right now in the
election cycle
but it is you know four years ago four
years ago plus three weeks
in which the then sitting president who
knew that he would not continue to be
the president
was advising the senate to get on with
it and
fill a vacancy right so um
i have almost no doubt barack obama will
not come out in favor of filling the
vacancy
um this time but i want people to think
a little bit if they haven't already
at what the implications are of filling
or not filling the vacancy first of all
we are in a situation where people are
um
war gaming possible scenarios over
a contested election of one version or
another where ballots can't be certified
there are many scenarios in which an
election might end up in the supreme
court
the fact of a supreme court that now has
an even number of people
on it rather than an odd number of
people means that one of the solutions
that could be relied upon to save us
from a catastrophe in which the nation
tore itself apart over
differing opinions over who should
ascend to the presidency
is now potentially off the map
it's the difference between an even
number and an odd number the difference
between an even number and an odd number
what's more the democrats and
um you know again it's very interesting
that we have
a mirror image of this scenario in the
2016 election
but the democrats have a lot
riding on the idea that one
absolutely has no choice but to vote for
biden no matter what you think of him
blue no matter who because
the next president will certainly be
replacing ruth bader ginsburg
right now it's not just ruth bader
ginsburg but the fact that she has died
and could plausibly be replaced
on the court before the election
robs the democrats of an argument that
they are using to badger people
into not thinking for themselves right
so
as somebody who you know sticks just got
higher the stakes just got higher and if
trump manages to seat a justice on the
court
ahead of time the stakes um
drop and because they drop those
who have been badgered into
signing up with the democratic party
would
be freed in some sense you know not
fully but the degree of pressure that
people
face when they talk about alternatives
to the duopoly
that pressure would drop somewhat and so
anyway
this of course opens a
strategic play for the president and you
know
you and i are no fans of the president
but
um we do recognize that he has
sufficient political insight to have
actually defeated one of the duopoly
powers and taken over
the gop so it is not beyond
him in any way to see that he has an
opportunity here
especially if he was to quickly
nominate somebody who was like
ginsburg capable of
reaching across the aisle appealing to
people on both sides
you know unimpeachable in terms of their
character
right were he to do a character in their
history right
right in other words if he were to find
just the right person then the democrats
for strategic reasons
would i believe um be hostile to that
nomination
uh and would be revealed to be
as cynical and political as the dnc has
has made the party and that would be a
win for trump
so um
this is a this is a very powerful shift
in the electoral landscape
for many different reasons at many
different levels and
i don't know what's going to happen but
i would say
my guess is this works for trump and
against the democrats and that the
democrats to the extent
that they are actually interested in the
long-term
well-being of the nation would be wise
to move
very very carefully they should really
think about what they're doing and they
should not
just simply play the same disastrous
political game that they have been
uh so strenuously advocating for so long
so you're advocating that they come up
with a new game right now
i'm advocating as they wake the hell up
all right so neither of those things
your framing or mine
come up with a new game or wake the hell
up are likely to happen
well um yes on the other hand
this um the fact
of them being proactive in trying to
shut down the idea of seeding
a justice um and you know
playing with bizarre ideas like adding
members to the supreme court making it
an 11-person court in order to
you know they're they're just that's
been proposed oh yeah
oh yeah just newly as if as if i think
it's an idea that has been
circulating my sense is that it is an
idea that has been circulating
um and that you know look there's a lot
of uh skulls
i've never what is the justification i
mean nine
nine is a lot nine is odd um
it seems to me that a justification for
that
you know really the the only one that i
come up with immediately
is so transparently political that no
way does whatever party is not in power
agreed to it which is that
we've decided to do that and at the
moment we decide to do it our president
gets to appoint the two new people um is
there is there any legitimate
reason for an 11 versus a nine person
court i mean there may well be it just
doesn't i've never heard this before and
nothing comes to mind
i do not believe so i believe that this
is um
nakedly political now i do not want to
say nakedly political is just a feature
of the democrats when it comes to the
supreme court the democrats would tell
you that they are
responding to nakedly political stuff
from the right and there has been quite
a bit
so um it is not as if that game is
imagined on their part
nonetheless it is the uh
it is exactly this argument that you
know
they packed the court now we're going to
pack the court um kind of thing and
we're going to bend the rules and
do it our own way that that motivates
this as far as i can tell
i mean i guess i just i want to keep
coming back to this idea that ginsburg
herself
was uh looked at somewhat askance
by some feminist leaders at the time
because she had worked
across the aisles and she and across the
aisle isn't the right uh metaphor for
the judiciary but
that she had worked with judges who were
understood to be conservative yeah that
she had
um that and i i think i may have this
wrong but i think that she and scalia
actually had a friendship like you know
and they they were probably as
as far opposite on the polls um
politically on the court
when they were both on the court as as
existed and yet
you know this language that i read from
both of them they were both right
like they and you know until
until today i'd never read anything of
scalia's i think
and if you had asked me what his what
his
uh dissents or or statements would have
sounded like
uh i would i wouldn't have guessed that
they were
that i could have found so much to agree
with in them
well and this this is a lesson you know
again
in and around the concept of unity this
is a constant lesson
it is amazing how frequently now what
we thought uh what we heard people say
and thought was
true just seems preposterous right like
i i in my mind i keep returning to the
concept of mitt romney as
the greater evil right that we had to
pull out
all of the stops to stop mitt romney at
a point you know
where you know that that argument was
local to a moment in history and the
fact that the very people making that
argument
um are now you know lamenting the fact
that you know
if only the guy on the other side was
romney because you know now we have the
real greater evil right
yeah um so so actually to go back to one
of your points though so you
what did you say one of the five most
important
things in the universe principles
principles in the universe uh
is that uh people need to have
discretion in order to
humanize laws that's not exactly what
you know what you want to say yes that
um functional complex
systems human systems require
discretion to be functional so yes
and uh one of the things that
that ginsburg was fighting for
throughout her career was the ability
for people
for men to see the effects
of the the laws that were on the books
on women
when in her experience what um men in
the judiciary and other men
of power would say was but
i care deeply for and make opportunities
for
my daughter my niece my granddaughter
whatever
so you know wha what's wrong and so what
we can't do
is have discretion held within
particular demographics we cannot have
discretion held
by men over women by white people over
black people by black people over white
people by women over men
anything right discretion has to be
available
within for for any decision
but that too has to be at the individual
level and not decided
in advance by the demographic that you
haven't
been born to or have chosen to be part
of and i
totally agree with that and you have to
have the people
who are in a position to wield that
discretion you have to pick
honorable people who are capable of the
nuance and inclined
to do the right thing right which is not
impossible but not simple
but they have to be in a context that is
hospitable
to them doing the right thing which is
exactly why the founders
gave the supreme court justices tenure
for life
right you have to be freed from the
people who wanted their bidding done
when they advanced your candidacy to be
the person employing the discretion you
have to be freed from their influence
that's right and this this is a place
where tenure for life is functional
right there's we could we could speak
for weeks about whether or not tenure in
the university system
uh is a good idea and if it is
effectively worked
one of the ways it has not worked is
that often people once they get tenure
become less productive they become lazy
they do less and they just
stay on the same whatever path they were
on they become canalized in the language
of developmental biology right
um and of course that's just not a
possibility
on the supreme court you can't become
lazy and stop being productive
uh you you are going to show up
constantly
and continue to do your work um
i wouldn't say can't okay and the
example that i would pick
and i'm you know i should really go back
and look at what the history has been
but
at the point that justice thomas
ascended to the court
he had an extremely strong tendency to
simply reproduce scalia's vote
sure and so that does strike me as
but that's not i i remember this too and
uh i remember being very frustrated by
the whole situation but
um that isn't inherently about laziness
or not being productive
um i think the the
level of agreement the the fact that
as i recall it seemed like lockstep it
wasn't even
lockstep it was like scalia made a
decision and
basically he was a supreme court justice
with two votes
yeah right um now presumably uh that
tendency has been broken by scalia's
death which
it's hard to follow in his footsteps yes
exactly yeah um but
in any case tenure for life is
inherently going to have
a downside right and you know we saw
this
at evergreen where um we saw lots and
lots of faculty members who
had tenure and you know were
dead wood at best they were dead wood in
the system you just couldn't get rid of
them and that's you know
we saw that in in other places as well
yeah i think ev
every every system of higher ed with
tenure
has this problem there's a tension there
yeah and you know it's the tenure is
supposed to give you
the freedom to go outside of the overton
window basically
right the freedom to challenge the
status quo
and to explore things you haven't felt
secure enough to explore before because
uh you may fail or your answers may be
ugly
there are a lot of reasons to not ask
certain kinds of questions when
you are trying to figure out whether or
not you're going to have money to pay
the rent
and at the point that you know that
you've got job security potentially the
argument goes you can
you can open it up you can open up all
of those things that you were sort of
carefully tending but not
not working on explicitly um and and
move forward with them
um all too often we see the opposite
yeah
all right so i think we're at um an hour
zach
an hour and seven minutes so i would
just to close this out i would say
what i'm actually hoping will happen is
that the president
will advance a uh a
nominee quickly who is
um not divisive
somebody who does have unimpeachable
character and
does work across um party lines now
i don't think there's anyone who is not
divisive well
depends what you mean um i believe
there are people who fit the bill the
problem is
the president um
will i think have to
nominate someone who is uh
hostile to roe v wade for political
reasons
i don't think he could in his position
do anything but that
and that's that's that's the only thing
that you need for it to be
divisive and you know we don't we won't
do it here today because we don't have
time but
um you know many
extraordinary legal scholars will say
that
uh as you know as apparently ruth bader
ginsburg
did uh that while you know
you might disagree but many people will
say
i want abortion to be constitutionally
constitutionally protected
and that decision was not the right
decision
so how do how do we move forward with
those two things simultaneously
um especially when as soon as you even
begin to consider dismantling a decision
which might not have been the right
decision for legal reasons
and half the come i don't know what the
what percentage but you know a
considerable part of the country really
doesn't does not want this right
protected
how is it that you move forward and so
you know clinging to
a 1973 decision that may have been
constitutionally not very robust but is
a right that has provided
a freedom to you know 46 years of women
now
that you know many of us
uh would be terrified to see lost what
what do you do
i don't know i don't know so i would
point out that what's at stake here
is actually greater as important as this
question is what's at stake here is
actually far greater because
the role that roe v wade as the
protector
of um reproductive rights
has played has been absolutely
diabolical this has empowered
um the duopoly above all other things
because maybe not above all others but
really maybe the second amendment is the
only competitor that's abortion in two
way those are the two big things
right so the point is this has hung like
a sword of damocles
over anybody who would contemplate
a less divisive better political
environment
it the tyranny that has come to us all
from the fact that this contentious
right has hovered
um you know in jeopardy uh is
has been a disaster it's a bit like uh
anti-castro
cubans who held uh
such power over presidential politics
for for so long in florida
that there's just the disproportionate
impact of this is not fundamentally
reproductive it's about things like
political corruption and its ability to
remain lodged in our
in our political structures and so what
i would say is
the roe v wade decision um
was i believe cruddy from the point of
view
of its basis it was actually
a good match in terms of what it
protected
it was a good match for what the vast
majority of americans want the vast
majority of americans
are not wildly enthusiastic about
abortion as they shouldn't be they
um don't like it um but
they do believe the original i mean roe
v wade actually lays out different
um rights by trimester absolutely which
has since been
modified but um you know really
if i remember correctly first trimester
abortion at will
without explanation or justification
required by the mother
second trimester safety of the mother
the safety of the mother
um and maybe um or um
known to be massive genetic or
developmental anomalies in the fetus i
think
um and actually i'm not sure that's
that's right because i think the third
one is only is
is the third trimester is only about
life of the mother um so i don't i don't
think you have that right for the second
trimester it's some it's something
intermediate and um and
gosh you know the vast majority of
people
actually fall somewhere in that
the idea that you should be able to have
an abortion the day before the kid would
be born is insane
it's nuts and and most people also don't
think that zygotes are god's will
right so so so what i would argue is a
couple of things
one leaving roe as the protector of this
right is disastrous because of what else
it does to our political structure
right so it's possible that we need a
better protection one that's founded
on a sounder set of legal principles you
know rather than
privacy right protected by the fourth
amendment but
it is also possible that somebody who
[Music]
is not favorable to abortion rights but
is favorable
to the you know starry decisis for
example which is the
legal principle by which settled law is
not
revisited by the court that
you could find somebody who was
satisfactory
and unimpeachable and that were the
president to do that
um it would a put the democrats in a
very interesting spot
and b uh probably be the right thing for
the nation
yup no i think that's um
i think that's possible it is it is
complicated
allow me to just say um zach if you
would show this for a moment that i
since we probably triggered a lot of
people with a discussion of abortion at
all
um i did write something i guess it's
over two years ago now
um on abortion uh that's published in
area which um
if i get caught up on posting links i
will post in the
description for this video but um you
know more this
this was written um boy i think
yeah right as kennedy was retiring and
before kavanaugh was had been
um proposed i believe um so that's it
was the last time
that this was of such um supreme as it
were
importance so um let's see
are we are we there for the hour i mean
there's lots more that we could talk
about of course
so many things i thought we were going
to get to that we didn't so i don't know
if the if the universe hang uh
holds out we can see if we can revisit
them in the next
stream yeah we can talk about portland
police department university of chicago
english department
decolonizing your lawn decolonizing i
don't have a lawn
well then maybe you've done it success
is yours
either that or it's been fully colonized
by things that aren't grass
i think that's acceptable somehow oh
yeah right yeah no i think we never had
a lawn we just
we we just have forest so um
let us say in in parting
that it will be back in 15 minutes for
the q a
uh where we'll be taking your super chat
questions from this hour and from the
next hour
um also the dark horse membership at my
patreon
uh is um has been it's been
fun so far we've been doing these
private q and a's we've done three of
them so far once a month
and uh for people subscribing at the
five dollar and up
level and for people subscribing at the
11 and up level
uh we give you an opportunity once a
month in a 48 hour period
to propose a question and then we pick
the 20 or 25 that we want to go through
for a two hour
q a and just before we went live today i
made that
i made that live so right now um on my
patreon at 11
and up you can uh go and pose a question
that we might answer
in our next private q a which will be
not tomorrow but
next sunday and the private q and as i
will say have been
great they've been a lot of fun you know
they're they're they're much more
intimate obviously yes they're cozier
we sit 50 closer and
uh that's right we bring in everyone all
of the animals are here all the animals
are here and then a few
and then a few yeah um you know they're
they're good and we also are able um
because in real time there are you know
only you know maybe a couple hundred
people actually watching live and then
we leave them up for the other
subscribers to to see later
uh we can actually check in with the
chat sometimes so like last time we were
asking
we were talking about music a bit and um
anyway they're they're good they're fun
and uh we've been enjoying them a lot
and then either of our patreons you can
have access to our discord server and
what else like subscribe like subscribe
comment
uh spread it around clips
all of that um september is coming to
an end after having barely just begun
and then time standing still for what
felt like about six years so i don't
know what that means but it does mean
that also the uh
um the discussions on my patreon the
evolution discussion and the coalition
of the reasonable discussion
are are headed our way for whatever
comes after
september i think it's october i think
it's october yep yep
all right so we will see you in 15
minutes
um assuming consuming everything
assuming the world stuff assuming the
world still exists and the internet is
still functioning all right
be well
you